<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-16T11:59:47-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Blog</title><subtitle>Personal blog of Kevin Gibson</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Nobody Has a Magic Crystal Ball — Why Using Estimates to Plan Complex Initiatives is a Harmful Practice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Predictions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nobody Has a Magic Crystal Ball — Why Using Estimates to Plan Complex Initiatives is a Harmful Practice" /><published>2020-07-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Predictions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Predictions/">&lt;p&gt;We need to stop believing that estimates are a reliable input to the initiative planning process. Instead, we should plan and prioritize initiatives based on value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I saying that estimates have no place in the planning process? No, I’m not saying that. Estimation does have it’s place, when properly applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While estimation may work in low complexity, stable environments, it is generally not a reliable approach and usually causes more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider Healthcare.gov, originally estimated to cost $95 million dollars… &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HealthCare.gov#Statistics&quot;&gt;Actual cost was $1.7 billion or roughly 17 times the original estimate.&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, cost overruns of that magnitude are not entirely attributed to poor estimation, many other factors were at play in that debacle. That said, in all walks of life, there are volumes of examples to prove that estimation is an unreliable tool that should be applied carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why are we so bad at estimating?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are hard wired to drastically underestimate the actual time, cost and risk required to complete tasks, projects, initiatives etc. Even when past experience tells us that it will take longer, our brains short circuit and default to a “best case scenario” mental model, and we tell ourselves, “this time will be different.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is known as “Planning Fallacy”, a concept first introduced by Daniel Kahneman and Amos Tversky way back in 1979.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, planning fallacy happens when we try to estimate anything complex, we naturally apply our own personal bias, and skew our ability to be objective and estimate accurately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agile to the rescue!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using iterative and incremental software development practices i.e. “Agile” recognizes that by planning work in short cycles it becomes easier to estimate by referencing previous examples, patterns and results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the rub…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When estimation is used upfront, at a point in time in which the absolute least is known, and the estimate is considered reliable enough to serve as the basis for creating the release plan, budget, resourcing, and scope, then the delivery teams, whether Agile or not, are already trapped and potentially doomed to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this scenario, delivery teams are victims of a vicious cycle where expectation violently collides with reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is a truly really harmful and prevalent practice which ultimately affects customer perception, team engagement, employee attraction and referrals, and overall business performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, are you saying to never use estimation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to the start of this post, I’m not saying that estimates aren’t useful, there is a place for them, and I’m writing a follow up post to unpack how we can use estimates as an input to the overall planning process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we must acknowledge is that estimations are largely influenced by personal bias and so we must use them carefully to avoid causing undue harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll write a follow up post shortly to unpack alternative approaches to planning using a value based approach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kevin</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">We need to stop believing that estimates are a reliable input to the initiative planning process. Instead, we should plan and prioritize initiatives based on value.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/crystal.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/crystal.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Write Great OKRs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/How-to-write-good-okrs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Write Great OKRs" /><published>2020-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/How-to-write-good-okrs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/How-to-write-good-okrs/">&lt;p&gt;Writing great OKRs takes time, patience and practice… Here’s a list of important “Do’s and Don’ts” when getting started…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;definitely-do&quot;&gt;Definitely Do:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start with Values, Vision &amp;amp; Mission&lt;/strong&gt; — Before writing any OKRs, make sure your leadership team agree on the organizational Values, Vision and Mission. OKRs are a great way to distill the organizational Values, Vision &amp;amp; Mission into real actionable goals with measurable results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on Core Business Drivers&lt;/strong&gt; — Write OKRs that focus on improving the core business drivers like Reducing Lead Time on Customer Requests, Employee Attraction and Retention etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work Top Down&lt;/strong&gt; — OKRs work really well for turning big strategic organizational goals into reality… Skip the small fry tactical stuff, and think big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think Big, Deliver in Short Cycles&lt;/strong&gt; — Turning game changing ideas into measurable goals takes time. Write annual OKRs to capture and frame the big picture. Write quarterly OKRs to capture and deliver “slices” of the annual OKRs so that you can deliver value early and often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get Cross-Functional&lt;/strong&gt; — Thinking big means that every department is going to need to come together as a unit to deliver the big goal. OKR is a great way to get leaders away from locally optimizing their own departments and thinking as a “team of teams”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Balance Capacity&lt;/strong&gt; — OKRs are useless if your leadership has no capacity to deliver them. It’s important to evaluate your operational capacity and find the right balance. Defund anything that doesn’t align with your strategic OKRs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;definitely-dont&quot;&gt;Definitely Don’t:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use Meaningless Buzzwords&lt;/strong&gt; — Ditch the buzzwords. Keep the language simple. Every level of the organization should be able to understand what you’re trying to accomplish and how you’ll measure success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use Biz Babble&lt;/strong&gt; — ”We’re going to find synergies and exploit emerging opportunities in the marketplace” — Nope, nope, nope - go sit in the corner with Mr. Buzzwords over there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write OKR To-Do Lists&lt;/strong&gt; — OKR is NOT a means for leadership to draft the master to-do list for their teams. Full Stop. Do not do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use OKR as an Evaluation Tool:&lt;/strong&gt; — Measure employee performance based on how your people behave and collaborate, not by how many OKRs they got done this quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OKRs for EVERYBODY!!!&lt;/strong&gt; — If you’re giving OKRs to your interns, you’re doing it wrong!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kevin</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">Writing great OKRs takes time, patience and practice… Here’s a list of important “Do’s and Don’ts” when getting started…</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/bullseye.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/bullseye.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2 Minute Book Reviews</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Good-Reads/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2 Minute Book Reviews" /><published>2020-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Good-Reads</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Good-Reads/">&lt;p&gt;Micro book reviews from my reading list…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/accelerate_book_cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Accelerate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accelerate&lt;/strong&gt; — &lt;em&gt;Nicole Forsgren, PhD, Jez Humble &amp;amp; Gene Kim&lt;/em&gt; — A hugely important and influential book. Should be required reading for any manager working in dev, product, agile, devops etc. It’s no surprise this was the book of the year in 2018… Humble &amp;amp; Kim are practically the Godfather’s of DevOps. In this book they partner with Nicole Forsgren, PhD to prove that the mindset, behaviours and practices of DevOps produce real business results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/SAGE_cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Accelerate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solutions for Agile Governance in the Enterprise (SAGE)&lt;/strong&gt; — &lt;em&gt;Kevin W Thompson, PhD&lt;/em&gt; — Is your Agile Transformation going sideways? Are your Agile Coaches shrug their shoulders and say “We told you Agile was hard, here’s your invoice”? If so, grab a copy of this excellent book from Kevin Thompson, PhD. He’s the principal consultant at CPrime and in this book he offers loads of practical advice to make Agile work in the Enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kevin</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">Micro book reviews from my reading list…</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/bookshelf.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/bookshelf.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Comic of the Month</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/comic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Comic of the Month" /><published>2020-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/comic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/comic/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;chairs--pants&quot;&gt;Chairs &amp;amp; Pants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Dilbert_Chairs_and_Pants.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dilbert_Chairs_and_Pants&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kevin</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">Chairs &amp;amp; Pants</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/noun_eyes_21263.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/noun_eyes_21263.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Effective principles that work with any methodology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/mindset/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Effective principles that work with any methodology" /><published>2020-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/mindset</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/mindset/">&lt;p&gt;I recently stumbled upon these wise words from Doc Norton from OnBelay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this because it cuts right to the heart of what matters most in software development. I’ve seen too many teams get caught up in the mechanics of their chosen frameworks, rather than focusing on what really matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Work together.&lt;br /&gt;
Create simple things in small steps.&lt;br /&gt;
Be meticulous about composition.
Validate before, during, and after.&lt;br /&gt;
Know the problem you are solving.&lt;br /&gt;
Release ridiculously often.&lt;br /&gt;
Automation over documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attribution:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://onbelay.co/doc-norton&quot;&gt;Doc Norton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Doc’s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://leanpub.com/escapevelocity&quot;&gt;Escape Velocity&lt;/a&gt; on Leanpub&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kevin</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">I recently stumbled upon these wise words from Doc Norton from OnBelay.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/einsteing_big.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/einsteing_big.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Great Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/25-great-quotes-on-software-development/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Great Quotes" /><published>2020-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/25-great-quotes-on-software-development</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/25-great-quotes-on-software-development/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;productivity&quot;&gt;Productivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Stop Starting. Start Finishing. — &lt;strong&gt;Sterling Mortensen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;business-agility&quot;&gt;Business Agility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Startups develop their software in profit centers; they haven’t learned about cost centers yet. And in a competitive battle, a profit center will beat a cost center every time. — &lt;strong&gt;Mary Poppendieck&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We do not rise to the level of our goals. We fall to the levels of our systems. — &lt;strong&gt;James Clear&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;leadership--values&quot;&gt;Leadership &amp;amp; Values&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;True values are not taught and declared, they evolve through the acts and interaction of the living, they are understood at near tacit level by those who live them. — &lt;strong&gt;Dave Snowden&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Responding to Change OVER Following a Plan” is not the same as “Winging it OVER Having a Plan” — &lt;strong&gt;Doc Norton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you only quantify one thing, quantify the cost of delay — &lt;strong&gt;Don Reinertsen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do not go where the path may lead, go instead where there is no path and leave a trail” — &lt;strong&gt;Ralph Waldo Emerson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>kevin</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">Productivity</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/megaphone.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/megaphone.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Top 10 DevOps Books</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/john-wilis-top-10-devops-books/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Top 10 DevOps Books" /><published>2020-04-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/john-wilis-top-10-devops-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/john-wilis-top-10-devops-books/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;john-willis-knows-devops&quot;&gt;John Willis knows DevOps…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last couple years, I’ve read a lot of books on Lean, Agile, Product, Business, DevOps, Analytics, Training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only recently discovered how brilliant John Willis is after listening to the audiobook of Beyond The Phoenix Project - The Origins and Evolution of DevOps by John Willis and Gene Kim…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The depth of knowledge that John has is actually a little bit scary or inspiring…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I stumbled upon a Medium article where he listed out his own Top Ten DevOps books and so I thought I’d add them here for future reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-top-10&quot;&gt;The Top 10:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Phoenix Project: A Novel about IT, DevOps, and Helping Your Business Win&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effective DevOps: Building a Culture of Collaboration, Affinity, and Tooling at Scale&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accelerate: The Science of Lean Software and DevOps: Building and Scaling High Performing Technology Organizations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continuous Delivery: Reliable Software Releases through Build, Test, and Deployment Automation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practice of Cloud System Administration, The: Designing and Operating Large Distributed Systems, Volume 2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liquid Software: How to Achieve Trusted Continuous Updates in the DevOps World&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leading the Transformation: Applying Agile and DevOps Principles at Scale&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Unicorn Project: A Novel about Developers, Digital Disruption, and Thriving in the Age of Data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making Work Visible: Exposing Time Theft to Optimize Work &amp;amp; Flow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The DevOps Handbook: How to Create World-Class Agility, Reliability, and Security in Technology Organizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>kevin</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">John Willis knows DevOps…</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/devops_big.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/images/devops_big.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>